hello and welcome everyone this is the
active inference Institute cly Round
Table number one for the year on March
29th 2024 so welcome Alex thanks
everyone we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the links on this
slide this is a recorded and an archive
live stream so feel free to provide
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll follow video etiquette
for live stream if you're watching along
live feel free to put any questions in
the live chat and we'll get to them at
the
end well today we're here in our first
quarterly update of the year we'll give
some updates and remarks at The
Institute scale then we'll take a look
at the edac and Reiner organizational
units covering the education and
research projects and just talk about
moving forward in
2024 before we jump in Alex do you want
to add
anything uh just just uh it will
celebrate
for now one year and the first round
table for this year thank you yeah feels
like a lot has already happened but I
guess that's why we snapshot it
quarterly so here we go into Institute
scale
updates starting with a big picture on
where things are at with the Institute
here in the center we have a
representation of The Institute and its
relationship with the
ecosystem we have Institute level
functions such as our officers Board of
director and scientific Advisory Board
who help Steward and guide directly or
indirectly the organizational units
focused on Education edac and Research
Reiner and underneath those
organizational units are all of the
projects that we're going to be talking
about through the projects is where
dissemination participation and
engagement occurs at The Institute as
well as some engagement types that we'll
be discussing more in a few slides that
are at the Institute scale related to
philanthropy and Partnerships and
following on from the quantum free
energy principle work of Chris fields in
the course that he taught last year we
have in this year begun a prepare and
measure dual form approach the
preparation and the measurement forms
are always open they're open to
proposals and measurements large and
small we use them for projects within
the Institute and we ALS also use it to
interface projects in the ecosystem the
proposal or the preparation form
describes what the project team is
setting up to operate or do and it
outlines explicitly how the team is
thinking about their contributions to
the accessibility rigor and
applicability of active inference also
teams are able to suggest minimal and
higher levels of support that the
Institute could provide so if nothing
else is needed from The Institute other
than a channel in a chat thread or a
certain other kind of small support then
things might just begin right then or
maybe they're waiting for some kind of
support or maybe they throw out a high
support offer and one day we hope to be
able to fulfill those in support of the
ecosystem and then the other side of the
coin or the other side of the action
perception loop as it were is the
measurement form which describes what
the person or the project or the team
did what did they see change and learn
and these measurements reports could be
about open- Source contributions to code
and educational materials that people
make it could be I read a page from a
book today and that enables visibility
communication and the flow of support to
projects so we hope that through this
project-based engagement and preparation
and measurements we'll have a lot of
very interesting affordances and
structures to include and accommodate
how to diverse our community and
ecosystem are which leads to a common
and Central and critical question which
is okay but how to participate well
suffice to say there's multiple ways to
be involved on your own timelines or on
ours and by even asking you've begun
onboard. active inference dorg is one
Landing point if you want to get more
involved we also have a Discord that you
can jump into and sending an email to
blanket active inference Institute is
also always a good way to get the
conversation going as for projects
mentioned on the previous slide you can
join synchronous listed meetings of
projects or if the time doesn't work or
you prefer another mode of Engagement
you can communicate with the project
facilitators so the activities page is
just like a roster or menu or a series
of
options affordances that you can design
your curriculum and tune it in and out
as you see fit for people looking to
have a more structured involvement with
projects as well as maybe to accelerate
on their personal active inference
Journey there are other programs that we
provide such as the Institute internship
and for saying updated on happenings in
the ecosystem more broadly we have a
newsletter and a video channel perhaps
one that you're watching right now and
so some of the paths through can look
like this beginning with staying updated
this phase could be 15 minutes for some
people it could be 15 years for some
people to learn and absorb read the
papers and the Publications that are
coming out about active inference and
related topics watch our videos follow
social media accounts and read our
newsletter and do your own things in the
ecosystem learn apply fly share your
work donate stay tuned for more
opportunities and so on and then across
the thin dashed line into the Institute
someone joins to contribute to a project
or just to find out what's going on in a
project curiosity is enough and maybe
moving on to participating in an
internship and really getting more
embedded and engaged with the active
inference community and blazing paths or
following whatever is important for you
on that personalized Journey so these
are just some of the ways to get
involved there's a lot to learn and
there's a lot to absorb and resource
sharing is a big piece of that and if
somebody wants to get in contact or get
more involved in the projects that we're
going to be describing here that is why
we are participatory that's why we're
here for everyone anything to add on
that
Alex
uh yeah I see it quite quite important
and valuable that uh new approach that
we propos and we implementing in terms
of using
preparation uh
forums and Al forms that reflects the
progress and I believe maybe for now for
people for for familiar with Institute
we should see it as developments that
they should pay attention and see how to
use them and for new possible
participants also to have more close
look on what fors because this approach
again is based on first principles and
uh it's provide ways and affordances for
us to organiz to organize work on
different physical scales and also time
scales thank you thanks
carrying on with some more Institute
scale updates here's a nice new
re-representation of some of the
organizational rhythms starting with the
quarterly we have the round table the
video we're in right now and also
quarterly meetings with our board of
directors this is our second cohort same
people but our second go around on a
monthly time scale we have meetings with
our scientific Advisory Board which is
an informal guidance and insight board
and day after day hour after hour our
Sab members make many important and
relevant contributions so we spoke with
them even yesterday and it's great to
continue those conversations and just
the
incredible backgrounds and approaches
that people bring and and how excited
and productive it can be when we're
working together all like this then on a
weekly time scale Alex blue and I
checking in as officers and on a daily
to subc time scale the actual inference
and activity of our community
itself also we're really excited to
today discuss a few upcoming programs
that are going to be developing in the
coming weeks Beyond where they have been
and um rolled out very soon the three
programs that that people will hear more
about in the coming months but if you're
interested in these programs if you have
Insight or experience in any of these
areas we're about to discuss or if you
feel like you or your organizations
might want to be some of the truly very
first in each of these categories please
get in touch and here are the programs
first for individuals we will be
deploying a research fellowship program
research resarch fellows will be
individuals who are affiliated with the
Institute officially in terms of being
able to list that on papers and having
an email address and so on to reflect
the alignment with their research and
contributions to active inference and
our open science approach will be
providing a variety of mechanisms to
enable and catalyze the Innovative work
and the discoveries that those fellows
make and future fellow programs we would
look to more materially support in
different ways and also expand outside
of research fellows into education
fellows and so on all these incredible
places we see active inference being
applied the partnership program will
provide a structured venue and Avenue
for organizations that are looking for
any numbers of several different things
including to make meaningful impactful
and recognized contributions to the
active inference open source ecosystem
for organiz ations that are looking to
upskill and accelerate their own active
inference learning and application to
form Regional and sector level
collaborations or collaborations
involving a certain language or approach
or
discipline important input that
organizations can provide to The
Institute about what we might do to be
the best supporting Organization for the
ecosystem possible and also build
positive reputation and context and
access community and talent as we know
that active inference Talent can be
sometimes a limiting factor and the last
program here is the philanthropic
Avenues these will constitute small and
large donations of different types to
support the sustainability and frankly
the viability of the institute's mission
and vision going forward currently our
501c3 tax exempt status is pending so
hence waiting until that is cleared to
move forward but we envision a Continuum
from monthly and smaller opportunities
for people to provide tax exempt
donations all the way on through very
large and custom philanthropic
relationships so if on the research
fellows organizational Partnerships or
philanthropic Avenues if any of those
sound exciting or you think I've been
waiting for this affordance then this is
it so please get in touch anything you
want to add on that
Alex no cool and then just a few little
summary pictures of our growing
engagement in Outreach and public
communications platform and the slow and
then all at once
growth of complex
systems let's go on to the edu active
organizational unit and briefly cover
some of our education oriented projects
so starting with the Institute projects
and these are just screenshots from our
activities page which is where you'll
land when you go to onboard. active
inference dorg this is just
screenshotted and snapshotted from there
today this is what is live right now
at The Institute we have several
educational projects first the active
inference ontology where we are
developing the the rigor and
applicability of the active inference
ontology as a core infrastructure for
The Institute and ecosystem this
facilitates the translation across human
languages computer languages and many
many other kinds of exciting
applications for really what is the
heart of active inference and people are
taking it in some very exciting
cosmological and mythological directions
too I know in audiovisual production we
produce a variety of informative and
interesting live streams and
podcasts I'll flip to that
slide in 2024 we've had 27 videos so far
we've had Sarah Hamburg with the morph
stream series continuing to look at uh
biomedic Computing techniques org stream
with a focus on organizational design
and applications of active inference
math stream with a focus on some of the
mathematical topics that are Central or
peripheral in active inference insights
the absolutely wonderful series that
Darius has been carrying out with many
guests and guest streams which are
oneoff events that allow us to hear from
a wide range of voices and projects in
the ecosystem just from sampling ranging
from Marshall mcluhan and Andrew
mccluhan carrying on that Legacy and
tradition through Knowledge Management
Adrien Bon with a constructal law
empirical status of predictive coding
and active inference open source AI
mental gravity Alexi tolchinsky uh
participant and also a researcher in the
area companies applying active inference
all over the world in their robotic
settings and wellness science through
the lens of active inference so just
hearing about all these exciting
things um if you have production skills
or interest please do consider joining
this very fun and accessible project
there are a ton of ways that people can
help ranging from curating and
suggesting inviting guests facilita in
streams in English or other language
improving Communications before during
and after videos all kinds of things
that people can do as well as work and
articulate the interface between our
production of audiovisual materials and
the processes at the octave inference
Journal which pick up where the live
stream ends and where other media leave
off and are able to integrate that into
our knowledge management approaches
provide transcription translations
captionings all these really critical
functionalities that we're developing
out and then last Institute educational
project is the textbook group so the
textbook group rolls on ever since the
March 2022 publication of this par pulo
and friston textbook so two years ago
this textbook being published and cohort
5 continues on with the second half of
the book cohort 6 continues with the
first half of the book we're having
great times we have people joining one
or both groups as they alternate across
different time spot spots week to week
we've had almost 400 registrations for
this group over the six cohorts so it
demonstrates the strong and continued
excitement and curiosity that people
have and also we know there's many other
reading groups and people enjoying and
curious about this book so for here I'll
just add that all backgrounds and levels
of familiarity with active inference
math statistics philosophy all of these
different topics that come into play all
these backgrounds are welcome and we
cherish their questions and curiosity
the textbook group is a great place to
jump in you might find that it's a
swimming pool you jump in and then
immediately can quickly route onto okay
well here's the more advanced way to
apply it computationally
or here's a deeper Corner in philosophy
that that makes me curious about or you
might find as many of us have that
rereading these 10 chapters again and
again is its own fun
cycle those are the Institute projects
and then facilitated by The Proposal
form which is always open we've been
really excited to host a variety of
other projects in the ecosystem
facilitated by those outside of the
Institute so first we have the
fundamentals of active inference with
sanjie namjoshi this has been continuing
on since last year and his textbook in
progress is an absolutely comprehensive
update to the educational materials
available so we'll look forward to
seeing more as that continues action
research on Collective foraging
negotiation of forages with Susan Hasty
a really exciting week by week Dynamic
project that very interesting things are
coming in and out of and some other
projects that we would love to hear more
about to be able to share but please
anytime feel free to go to the onboard.
active inference dorg and click around
and learn from the documentation these
projects their prior Works contact the
facilitators see how it's listed to get
involved so these are the education
projects that are active at The
Institute right now Alex anything you
want to add here
just that it's great to see such a lot
of different projects some of them is in
different formats group working and for
now in basic form for personal online
learning for physics and is information
processing and social sciences course so
we test in different format improving
them and that's
great yes thank you to everyone for
their bravery and commitment to jump in
and
propose and to let us know and measure
and just to be involved and to make
these projects something that actually
comes true and is enacted for our
diverse nestmates in the
ecosystem all right moving from
education onto the Reiner unit into the
research projects here's an analogous
snapshot of the research work happening
right now so we have three research
oriented projects research and
development or application at The
Institute first is the RX and fur. JL
Learning and Development Group this has
been a wonderful project we've gotten
deeper and deeper into the Julia
language package developed by bias lab
and colleagues called RX andf fur. JL
Julia language as well as some of the
anal itical formalisms that the package
uses like Factor graphs and message
passing may be new for some SL all but
we're having an awesome time in a large
group working through the examples from
coin tossing on through drone flight
we'll have a live stream with the
developers of the package next week to
talk more specifically about the active
inference drone setting and we really
look forward to the continued upscaling
of the community and the usage and the
applicability of RX infer which is just
a very exciting direction for active
inference in knowledge engineering we
continue to explore Avenues involving
more on the library science side the
archiving and curation of materials and
also more into the modern language
processing and Analysis space into the
large language models and different
kinds of collaborations there so many
threads that are developing and Brewing
which we hope to reveal more on soon and
an active block FR which is wrapping
active inference generative models from
different language of different styles
in CAD CAD which is a systems
engineering execution framework which
exists in Python rust and Julia so
thinking about the systems engineering
side of our work and about the
articulation between the specification
of composable active inference
generative model components and being
able to use those in an open source
systems engineering framework that's as
rich and full featured and first
principles as cat cat is so that's been
great
collaboration and we have a number of
research projects in the ecosystem we
have symbolic cognitive robotics from JF
Cloud here continuing his very unique
work on symbolic active inference not to
go into too much detail but the high
road is the same and you'll find a
different low road in this project and a
variety of proposed and active research
projects ranging from exploring PTSD M
Theory Humanity story of an uncertain
self soil biology and ant biology and
Beyond we look forward to hearing more
updates from these research projects and
sharing and highlighting their work as
we hear from
it anything you want to add on the
research side
Alex
nope okay well then here are some
closing comments just a couple Meme and
fun slides that I brought together this
morning meanwhile if you're watching
live please feel free to write any
questions whatever they're epistemic or
pragmatic value be in the chat and we
will look at them after this but just
wanted to give a few comments and
thoughts and just every day there's new
soup from which to draw hearty meals
from but I just wanted to put down a few
of these thoughts as we're seeing it
right now so one there are many waves
and kinds of active inference catalysts
frictions and Horizons for people and
organizations we know about the two ways
that agents are able to bound their
uncertainty and reduce it which is to
change the Mind through inference
attention and learning as well as to
change the world through action and this
made me think about the so-called
multiple Horizons model and whether we
see it in terms of these stacking
Horizon
based upon maintenance nurturing and
novel creation or whether we see the
Horizons in any other number of
different ways such as like what's the
hill that we're on right now and then
the next Hill and then the next Hill
after
that broadly and I look forward to
refining this with people is the first
horizon that we're on is the familiarity
awareness and skill right now the rate
limiting step in applying active
inference to
any system basically is not
computational resources it's not GPU
access it's people's familiarity and
fluency with active inference with the
onology with the process of generative
modeling with Statistics all these
different kinds of features that come
into play the second Horizon on this
image on the right is the software and
the methods so after getting to a basic
level of familiarity one may start to
bump up rather quick with limitations of
the tools and packages whether
fundamental limitations of the packages
that require basically like open source
updates to progress on or one's skill
and fluency with using that software or
toolkit like RX and fur and then there's
a deeper broader Horizon involving
hardware and Beyond ecosystems of shared
intelligence heterogenous Computing
substrates analog and Quantum wet wear
all these different kinds of deeper
approaches which over a given timeline
will have tremendous impacts in the
active inference
ecosystem but whether we choose to focus
on the first horizon which is the
accessibility and participation of
active inference with the ability to
make it more broadly understood and
applicable more game ready downloadable
press playable than it is
today whether we choose to focus on that
second Horizon of the utility provided
by software packages and then whether we
look into the deeper Tech Beyond even
that into the unconventional Computing
substrates Beyond Turin computation and
so on these are all places and times for
bold action to support active
inference I think it calls for
passionate holistic
responsivity I think it calls for
individual inquiry organization
commitments and eological
Partnerships and again where there is a
discrepancy where someone thinks well
there should be a machine learning
answer to this or there should be a
communication for that or there should
be a course made for this kind of person
there's two ways to deal with that
discrepancy either to update one's
beliefs that such a thing doesn't exist
and doesn't have to and then walk away
calmly or be that change and we hope
that the Institute can be the locus of
those those changes so again for
individuals and organizations who are
ready for that we want to continue that
conversation 2024 is a unique year I
mean in a sense every year is a unique
year but it's not so common that we have
a full true tetrahedral New Year 2024 is
a perfect tet year that hasn't happened
since
1771 and it won't happen again till 23
100 there's a few other ways to kind of
work with or play with our date which is
um of the ways listed here I'll just
read the last one we can think about two
as the external States the external
unity in multiplicity the zero as the
Gap the two as our blanket perception
and action on the inbound and outbound
and then four are internal states which
themselves compose a
tetrahedron all good and I'm sure
there's many other ways to see it but
just so fun that our year can reflect a
nice shape like this and also we think
more and more about these two ways that
stability and stationerity can appear
and one is the construction project
that's dead on the ground and the other
is the top in motion which has a
stationary ity and a stability even a
resiliency but you don't get a bigger
dead object to flip over and spin and
that's active
inference a few more random fun
thoughts
um thinking about epistemic modes and
tempos with a lot of people's great
feedback I wrote a short piece about
wayfinding in the infinite Imaginarium
ju deposing epistemic temp and modes and
thinking about the Dynamics of the
changes in the speed and type of
Journeys that we take in the epistemic
ecosystems we're in and then just
thinking about more
organizationally we had a lot of work
and deadlines and timelines in the fall
of 2023 leading up to a major NSF Grant
application which we didn't get and the
third applied active
inference uh ecosystem Symposium on
enacting ecosystems of shared
intelligence so that was fast and a lot
of other details coming into play
quickly and then December taking it slow
moving with the seasons and
consolidating to introduce the project
proposing measure dual always open form
system during this first quarter which
we discussed at the beginning and now
the game is a foot again things thicken
or Quicken there's the growth and the
development of projects in our space
there are many internal and external
flows that people are
innovating in and around every day at
The Institute and there's also growing
excitement and energy in the ecosystem
to say nothing of capital activity so
it's a very interesting time and one of
the images from the paper
by Long Way Around from Dean is this
idea of a gap an epistemic Gap and what
to do about that Gap it can be
appreciated and it can be crossed in
multiple ways it can be jumped across
that's the canal jumping Quantum
approach or it can be filled or a bridge
can be built over it and so what are
those epistemic gaps and how do we
determine how do we appreciate fill
bridge and jump different
gaps and then on a different wavelength
another paper here co-written several
weeks ago with Dean was about the
fourfield fields of quantum dreams and
it was a creative and exploratory piece
about visual perception and Quantum
active inference and all these topics
and there's just a few facts that I felt
were important to know the 1923 New York
Yankees 101 years ago they went 98 and
54 in the playoffs they Avenged their
previous losses by defeating the New
York Giants in six games four games to
two and they won their first world
series title so it was a big season for
the team Babe Ruth one of their
players had a 393 batting average and
some other great statistics
so on one hand it was absolutely
historic where talking about it now and
yet at at least two nested levels of
historical success the team scale and
the Slugger scale with the sample size
of well over a 100 games or at bats the
success rates were in the 35 to 65%
range Babe Ruth only was hitting less
than four out of 10 times going down six
out of 10 times and the team was only
winning 65% of the games and I think
about ants moving Pebbles and about
moving many 51% correctly gets a nest
and yet apparently to this baseball
history comes alive.com
reference what makes this Ruth's best
season ever was his outstanding
performance in the field he was the
American League's best right fielder so
despite the numbers that we can record
what made it the best was actually
something that was unrecorded so there's
so many fun little twists and turns in
that about what is recorded what is
unrecorded what are the success rates
and how do we just get up every day and
try again and keep it going across
multiple
scales so that we can appreciate fill
bridge and jump or not
appropriately and last memes
slide this is a dual railroad track
Vision in
Davis nearby me and I rewrote some
famous lines of
poetry I expect and prefer to tell this
with a sigh somewhere spaces and times
hence two roads diverged in a
could and we took the One Less Traveled
by and that enacted all the
difference here's Us in the moment of
decisioning and we have the
outside
dark not to do and then looking forward
we have more and more
affordances for what we can do and who
we can be and this Dove tells well with
a recent paper that the final version
came out today actually with MAO and
colleagues about shared protentions
which are prospections anticipations in
multi-agent active inference systems
which with the help of Toby and others
has now been explored in this category
theoretic
way
so I didn't want to have nothing here
and any something I know is partial
limited and incomplete and all these
different features but wanted to share
some of those ideas and mes and thoughts
in appreciation of all the amazing
contributions that people have made and
this kind of unique fractal nature of
our topic which is the
Divergence in what could be and
different ways that things could be and
what we do right there at the fork in
the road how do we take that fork how do
we stay with the trouble all these
different things that arise or are in
the Nexus of sense making and decision-
making so what a rich and exciting area
what a great time to be able to
collaborate and communicate with all so
many of you and we look forward to many
more fun times ahead so hope these last
slides made the right sense to you they
were just thrown together they aren't my
finest or only statements as such but I
did want to add them in here and so we
come to our last slide where since years
ago we've looked at and asked what would
an understanding enable what are the
predictions and
implications what are the next steps for
us and for the free energy principle and
for active inference what are our
preferences and what are you still
curious about so we will just uh
hear any last thoughts from Alex then
I'll look in the chat if there's any
questions and then in a few minutes as
soon as this ends we will just begin our
weekly open Office hours SL discussion
in the
Discord you can find the join Link in
the video description or elsewhere
otherwise um we'll just chill for a few
more minutes hear any questions that
people have and then just jump over to
having a open hour Alex what are your
kind of
thoughts yeah thanks for that last
slides very excit exciting and thank you
for sharing your ideas this way and uh I
believe these round tables are aimed to
show some information about instit in
this way for people for new people for
people who know us
and possibly have another look on
everything of it and even if you don't
understand for now uh how to join how to
participate but have uh general interest
to science to First principles to active
inference just give us a
sign send an email
or message in Discord and we'll find a
way how to support you in in that
Explorations and possible future
applications thank you thank you yeah
it's again there's there's so many
things to say and not say but it's
always amazing how people reach out and
um what active inference means to them
so if you're hearing this it's for you
if you're curious doubly so and uh this
year a lot is going to develop and
change the Institute will be
structurally
different with the increased numbers of
Affiliated
individuals with the development of a
real partnership group kind of like a
league or a Federation of organizations
that want to support active inference
ecosystem the education all the way on
through professional
applications and just providing some of
the Avenues that are more
recognizable as opposed
to the ones that are still not quite yet
on the radar but the chorus grows every
day of those who call for it to be that
way
so we need everyone to help Co create
that and be a part of that hence these
communications okay I'll look to the
live chat but write any questions if
there's anything that we can resolve
here otherwise this is a great
lengthened material for our update
here thank you hello blue nutrino memes
of Destruction upcycle Club
Susan okay fun fun discussions great
comments there but I don't see any
specific
questions all right um let's continue
the discussion anybody who wants to over
in our Discord right now if you're
watching this anytime blanket active
inference Institute and see you later
thank you thanks Alex thanks everyone
thank
you
for